Potter Club and Alumni Association; Records ua901.003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
The Edward E. Potter Club and Alumni Association Records
1911-2014
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua901.003
3.0 cubic ft.
The Edward E. Potter Club And Alumni Association Records includes documents and objects related to the finances, activities, and history of the Club and subsequent Alumni Association. Materials related to the Edward E. Potter Club include financial settlements, photographs, correspondence, and meeting minutes. Materials related to the Alumni Association include Alumni addresses, memorabilia, and a newsletter. Objects in this collection include mugs, a blanket, stamp, letter opener, compact makeup, and ledger books.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The Potter Club Records were originally donated to the University Libraries in 1989. Additional deposits were made by Don Kisiel in 1992 as well as John "Paul" Ward and Robert Umholtz in 1996-2011.
Biographical History
The Edward E. Potter Club, founded in 1931, began when 13 undergraduates and alumni proposed to form a club in order to promote close friendships in a non-fraternal organization. They called it the "State Union." Prior to the formation of the Potter Club, the only men's social group was the Kappa Delta Rho fraternity. The president of the college, Abram R. Brubacher, approved of another men's social club, but he did not like the name "State Union." Therefore, Brubacher suggested that the Club adopt the name of Edward E. Potter in memory of a student killed in France during World War I. The Potter Club Alumni Association, Inc., was incorporated on February 17, 1948. Headquartered in Albany, the Alumni Association facilitated communication between past and present members of the Potter Club, provided educational and financial assistance to Potter Club members through awards and scholarships, and promoted the interests of the University and its alumni.
Scope and Contents
The Edward E. Potter Club and Alumni Association Records document the origin, membership, activities, correspondence, financials, and memorabilia of the club from the 1930s to 2014. The Potter Club began in 1931 with 12 charter members. The club honored a collegiate who died in World War I, Edward E. Potter. The social club became a fraternity organization of SUNY Albany and focused on social events, the purchase of a fraternity house at 415 State Street, and the management of the club finances.
The collection includes multiple decades of the Potter Club's constitution and New York State Certificates of Incorporation, member evaluations, the Potter Post, correspondence, minutes of the Board of Directors, decades of alumni directories, and annual financial statements. The E.E. Potter Club transitioned into an Alumni Association in 1967. The members of the Potter Club Alumni Association redirected their focus as a SUNY organization to sponsoring an annual scholarship for a SUNY Albany student and continued to organize social gatherings for members. The records contain correspondence, minutes of Board of Directors, several issues of the Potter Club Alumni Newsletter, and alumni member ephemeral items. Memorabilia of the history of the club has been added to the collection from two decades of annual reunions and quinquennial anniversaries.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged chronologically. There are no series.
Class reunions; State University of New York at Albany--History; Correspondence; Financial Records; Ephemera; Publications; UAlbany Student Groups; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--New York (State); Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--New York (State)--Periodicals; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--New York (State)--Societies, etc.--Administration; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--New York (State)--Societies, etc.--Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Edward E. Potter Club and Alumni Association
- Edward E. Potter, Biographical, 1911-1919; 1930; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Petition for Recognition of State Union, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Potter Club Members, Photographs and Lists, 1931; 1949-1956; 1959; 1965; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Constitution of Potter Club, 1931; 1963-1964; 1967; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Potter Club Evaluations, 1933; 1963; 1965; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Memoirs and Talk about E.E. Potter, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Ledger, Potter Club, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1948; 1950-1968; 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Potter Club-415 State Street House, 1948; 1955; 1993; 2001; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Certificates of Incorporation, 1948; 1960-1961; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Ledger Book, Board of Directors Minutes of Meetings, 1948-1961 (Oversized 3)
- Club Social Functions, 1950; 1953; 1963; 1966; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Internal Revenue Service Correspondence, 1950; 1962-1964; 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 20th Anniversary, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Compact, 1951 (Oversized 4)
- Wooden Paddle (1 of 2), 1951 (Item 1)
- Wooden Paddle (2 of 2), 1951 (Item 2)
- Potter Post, 1952-1953; 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Composite Photographs, 1952; 1961; 1967; 1971-1972 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
- Potter Club Nightshirt, ca. 1955 (Oversized 6)
  General
  Donated by Paul Ward.
- 25th Anniversary, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Potter Club Letter Opener, 1956 (Oversized 4)
- Albany State Ceramic Stein, 1959 (Cd 3)
- Potter Club Housing, 1959; 1961; 1964; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- James Warden Memorial Scholarship, 1960; 1963-1964; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Financial Statements and Budgets, 1960-1965; 2012 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Origin, History, Purpose, and Meaning, 1960; 1965; 1970; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Potter Club Board of Directors Meetings, 1961; 1964-1968; 1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, Potter Men of the Year, 1961; 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Duties and Rules of Potter Club House, 1962; Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Potter Club Board Meetings, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- President's Register and Interfraternity Council, 1962; 1964; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Greek System: SUNY Albany and Non-SUNY, 1962-1966; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Potter Club House Expenses, 1962-1967; Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Supreme Court of the State of New York Appellate Division, 1963; Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Potter Club Meetings, 1963-1964; Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Potter Club Pledge List, Manual, Test, and Dedication, 1963; 1965; Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Potter Club Alumni Directory, 1963; 1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Potter Club Alumni Newsletter, 1963-1970; 1972-1976; 1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Wooden Paddle, Bob Fairbanks, 1964 (Item 3)
  Gift of Bob Fairbanks.
- Residence Hall Contracts, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Potter Club Letterman's Jacket, Patrick Pearson, 1965 (Oversized 7)
  Donated by Patrick Pearson.
- 35th Anniversary, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Central Savings and Loan Lawsuit, Supreme Court Answer, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Annual Meeting, Potter Club Alumni Association, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Financial Settlement, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Judicial Committee, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Correspondence, Robert J. Umholtz, 1970-1972; 1997; 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- 40th Anniversary, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Thomas E. Van Aken Memorial Scholarship, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- EEP, SUNYA Report, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Telectro-Mek Investment, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Obituaries of Members, 1989-2014 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, J. Paul Ward, 1995-2012 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Addresses of Potter Club Members, 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Opening the E.E. Potter Room at SUNY at Albany Alumni House, 1997 (Video-tape 1)
- Speech by Paul Ward, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- UAlbany Alumni Weekend, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- E.E. Potter Room, SUNY Albany, Alumni House, 1997; 2000; 2007-2008; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1997-2010; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Reunion, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Reunion, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Reunion, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Honoring E.E. Potter, 2001; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Reunion, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Potter Club Pen, 2003 (Oversized 6)
- Reunion, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Reunion, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Surveys, 2005; Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Addresses of Potter Club Members, 2005-2006; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Luncheons, 2005; 2008; 2013; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- 75th Anniversary, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- 75th Anniversary Glass, 2006 (Cd 3)
- E.E. Potter Family History, 2006; 2008; 2011; Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Plaque at Union College, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Reunion, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Reunion, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Reunion, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- 80th Anniversary, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Banner-80th Anniversary, E.E. Potter Club, 2011 (Map-tube 1)
- Banner Commemorating E.E. Potter's Birth, 2011 (Map-tube 1)
- Reunion (1 of 2), 2011 (Cd 1)
- Reunion (2 of 2), 2011 (Cd 2)
- Photographs, 2011; Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Honoring W. John "Jack" Higham, 2011-2012; Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Donations, 2012 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Banner Pieces, Insignia, and Decorations, Undated (Oversized 2)
- Corporate Seal Stamp, Undated (Oversized 4)
- EEP Glass Stein (1 of 2), Undated (Cd 3)
- EEP Glass Stein (2 of 2), Undated (Cd 3)
- E.E. Potter Training Photo Cornell, Undated (Cd 3)
- Literary Reference to Potter Club, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Memories Display for Reunion (1 of 2), Undated (Flat-file 1)
- Memories Display for Reunion (2 of 2), Undated (Flat-file 2)
- Phonograph Record, 45 format, "Music for Saylesman", Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Poems Written on E.E.P. Stationary, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Potter Club Blanket, Undated (Oversized 1)
- Potter Club Canvas Tote, Undated (Oversized 4)
- Potter Club Charm Bracelet, Undated (Oversized 4)
- Potter Club Jacket, Undated (Oversized 6)
- Potter Club Ledger Book, Undated (Oversized 2)
- Potter Club Letterhead and Stationary, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Potter Club Letterman's Jacket, Bob, Undated (Oversized 8)
  Donated by Bo Umholtz.
- Potter Club Pins, Undated (Oversized 4)
  Donated by Bernard Kerbal, Class of 1933.
- Potter Club Songs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Potter Club Sweater Patch, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Donated by Stanley Gipp, Class of 1947.
- Potter Club Sweatshirt, Undated (Oversized 6)
- Potter Club Tie, Undated (Oversized 6)
- Turquoise Box, Undated (Oversized 4)
- Wooden Paddle, Cole, Undated (Item 4)